Shizhi, don't forget.
适之你可别忘了
Behind us.
咱们身后
There's also a Japan that's waiting for you.
还有一个虎视耽耽的日本呢
Brother Zhongfu, what do you think.
仲甫兄你怎么看
I agree with Shizhi.
我同意适之的观点
I have studied a lot of Wilson's speeches.
我研究了很多威尔逊的演讲
I think he is a gentleman. .
我觉得他是个君子
He made two suggestions.
他提出两条建议
Countries are not allowed to take power.
不许各国拿强权
To violate the equality and freedom of other countries. .
来侵害别国的平等自由
Governments are not allowed to take power. .
不许各国政府拿强权
To violate the equality and freedom of the people. .
来侵害百姓的平等自由
I thought about it.
我琢磨了一下
As long as you do these two things .
只要做到这两点
Then justice must triumph over power.
那公理必定战胜强权呀
So I'm going to .
所以我打算
In the next issue of Weekly Review.
在下一期的 《每周评论》上
Come and write an article.
来写一篇文章
Let's have a good talk.
来好好地说一说
The best person in the world.
这个世界上的第一好人
Shouchang, can you also write a Paris Peace Conference?
守常你也写一篇巴黎和会吧
But I'm not that interested in America.
我可对美国没那么大兴趣
You know what?
这样吧
Let me write an article about the October Revolution in Russia.
我写一篇俄国十月革命的文章吧
It is also inclusive.
也行 兼容并蓄
史鸷你呢.
适之 你呢
Maybe next time.
我下次吧
I've been too busy recently.
我最近太忙了
Which one of us is the busiest?
你说咱们三个谁最忙啊
You.
你呀
You must be.
你呀 肯定是
fault.
不是
I think it's Shizhi.
我觉得还是适之
Why?
为什么呢
Because he works hard every day.
因为他每天工作的时间紧呀
You have to go to bed at ten o'clock in the evening.
到晚上十点必须上床啊
The Homemaker.
家有贤妻
Otherwise, don't let in. .
要不然不让进门
Are you two done?
你们俩有完没完
Come on in.
来进来吧
I'm really impressed with you.
真服了你们了
十堰.
世炎
Can all these books be sold? .
这么多本书能全卖出去吗
Brother Ge said that they are in Changxindian.
葛大哥说他们长辛店
There are thousands of people.
有上千人
Maybe it's not enough to sell.
搞不好还不够卖呢
I also bought some.
我也买了一些
New magazines and newspapers.
新发行的杂志和报纸
Sure enough, everyone is here now.
果然现在大家都在
Pay attention to this Wilson.
关注这个威尔逊
Even Liang Qichao.
就连梁启超啊
Also wrote an article "League of Nations and China".
也写了一篇《国际联盟与中国
Wilson's League of Nations.
说威尔逊的国际联盟啊
It is the best means to realize a harmonious world.
是实现大同世界的最好手段
Didn't Mr. Shouchang write .
守常先生不是写了
Two articles about Russia?
两篇介绍俄国的吗
New Era and Victory of Bolshevism.
《新纪元》和《布尔什维主义的胜利》
I bought that, too.
那个我也买了
But it seems that now everyone.
但是好像现在大家
Let's pay more attention to Wilson.
还是关注威尔逊多一些吧
Brother Zhao.
赵大哥
You see, now people are interested in violent revolution.
你看吧 现在大家对于暴力革命
There is still conflict.
还是有抵触的
I said, what's wrong with your two brothers recently?
我说你们哥俩最近是怎么了
When it comes to violent revolution.
一 提到暴力革命
It's like seeing the god of plague.
就跟见了瘟神似的
Think about it. Since ancient times .
你想想看从古至今
Which reactionary regime?
哪一个反动政权
Is to withdraw from the stage of history.
是自行退出历史舞台的
Which violent revolution since ancient times?
从古至今哪一场暴力革命
There is no bleeding.
没有流血特的
The reactionaries cannot be defeated.
没有流血轴性的
This is common sense and law.
这是常识 是规律
Russian October Revolution.
俄国的十月革命
Is to defeat the reactionaries.
不就是打倒了反动派
Established the people's political power.
建立了人民政权
Can ordinary people live a good life? .
老百姓才能过上好日子吗
How do you know the Russian people?
你怎么知道俄国的老百姓
Have a good life now.
现在过上好日子了
But I hear all countries are blocking them now. .
我可听说各国现在都在封锁他们
Domestic rebellion continues. .
国内叛乱不止
Let me tell you.
我给你说
Take a long-term view of the problem.
看问题眼光要放长远一点
The replacement of old and new social systems.
新旧社会制度的更选
It takes a long struggle.
是需要经过长期奋斗的
There is no problem with your long-term vision.
你眼光放长远没有问题
All right, let's not argue.
行了 别争了
Grandpa, give me a hard push.
各位爷爷使劲帮忙推一把
Come on, come on.
来使劲来
fast.
快
Brother Ju Ren.
菊人兄啊
I was specially called here today, and I was specially given a painting.
今日特意把我叫来 又特意赠画
I'm afraid it's not in the bar.
怕是醉翁之意不在酒吧
clever.
聪明
Tang Bo Lu Zhengxiang is going to Paris soon.
伯棠陆征祥马上要去巴黎了
This diplomatic stall.
外交这摊子
Chen Zhuan alone is the acting chief.
光靠陈篆这个代理总长
It won't hold up.
是撑不起来的
So at this juncture.
所以这个节骨眼上
You can't think about hiding at leisure.
你可不能想着躲清闲哪
You foreign affairs Committee .
你这个外交事务委员会
In my presidential palace.
就是我总统府里
The decision-making body of foreign affairs.
外交事务的决策机构
How to talk in Paris is up to you. .
巴黎那边怎么谈 全听你的
Brother Ju, fool the ghost.
菊人兄 你糊弄鬼吧
A Cao Rulin.
一个曹汝霖
Will be able to veto my proposal.
就能够把我的提案给否决了
I think it's hard for me to do anything.
我看 我是难有作为啊
Can't be pessimistic.
不能悲观啊
It's hard to be treated as a victorious country.
好不容易得到一个战胜国待遇
You have to do something. .
你我得有所作为呀
This is a godsend opportunity.
此乃天赐良机
Heaven is responsible for it.
天降大任哪
Now there is a difficult problem to decide.
现在就有个难题要决策
You said.
你说
We went to Paris for peace talks with five people.
我们去巴黎和谈去了五个人
But they gave our negotiators.
但是他们给我们的谈判的代表
Only two people.
只有两个人
Who is the permanent representative in charge of the talks?
谁当常任代表负责主谈
This candidate is crucial.
这个人选至关重要
Lu Zhengxiang is the chief representative.
陆征祥是首席代表
There is one seat left.
还剩一个席位
Let them take turns to attend.
让他们几个轮流出席吧
Absolutely not.
万万不能
This Lu Zhengxiang is in poor health. .
这个陆征祥身体不好
Live in Switzerland for a long time.
长时间住在瑞士
Wang Zhengting knows nothing about diplomacy.
王正廷根本不懂外交
Can't be the master.
不能当主谈
What do you mean?
那你的意思
My opinion is.
我的意见是
Let Gu Wei fish rank second.
得让顾维钓排名到第二位
Let him be the master.
让他当主谈
There must be no trouble in the south.
那南边还不得闹事啊
So this thing.
所以这件事
You have to be the big president to make decisions. .
得让你这个大总统出面决策
Tell them to take care of the overall situation.
叫他们都顾全大局
good.
好
I will do as Chairman Wang said.
我就按汪委员长的话去做
This picture is too good.
这张画太好了
Yannian.
延年
Come and help me classify these new books.
你来帮我把这批新书分一下类吧
Be sure to check it out. .
一定要检查清楚
line.
行
When I finish distributing the newspapers.
等我把报纸分完的
okay.
好的
Qiaonian.
乔年
Come and share the newspaper with me when you are finished. .
忙完了来跟我分报纸啊
good.
好
Yes, sir.
先生好
hello.
你好
thank you.
谢谢
Yes, sir.
先生好
hello.
你好
Prynne worked hard.
白兰 辛苦了啊
Yes, sir.
先生好
Hello, everyone. Hello, Mr. Shouchang.
大家好守常先生好
寿昌先生.
守常先生
I haven't seen you for some time.
好些时候没见着您了
Estimate your time.
估计您这段时间
Are you the busiest person in Peking University?
是北大最忙的人了吧
How do you say this?
此话怎讲
Look, you are the director of the library.
您看 您既是图书馆主任
It's New Youth again.
又是《新青年》
And the editor of the Weekly Review.
和《每周评论》 的编辑
Or the new magazine "National".
还是新杂志《国民》的
Editor in chief and writer.
主编和撰稿人
Recently, you have.
最近这段时间您又
Based on the Youth Reading Club.
以青年读书会为基础
And founded the Marquez Research Institute.
发起并成立了马尔克斯研究会
And you often.
而且您还经常
Go to Changxindian factory for research and investigation.
去长辛店工厂研究调查
Do you say there is anyone busier than you?
您说 还有比您更忙的人吗
Not the Marquez Institute.
不是马尔克斯研究会
It's the Marx Society.
是马克思研究会
I remember it was the Marquez Institute.
我记得是马尔克斯研究会啊
It's Marquez.
确实是马尔克斯
Mr. Wang deliberately called it Marquez.
先生有意称其为马尔克斯
Not Marx.
而不是马克思
Just to make people think that we .
就是为了让别人觉得我们
It's a society that studies Malthusian demography.
是研究马尔萨斯人口论的学会
So the authorities won't get into trouble.
这样当局就不会找麻烦了
Marx's research will cause trouble. .
研究马克思还会惹麻烦
I'm here with Mr. Dazhao this time. .
这段时间我在大钊先生这儿
Read some books by Marx.
读了一些马克思的书
Or deeply inspired.
还是深受启发的
Nice!
不错啊
It's time to start.
现在开始
Read Marxist books consciously.
自觉读马克思主义的书了
Students, our book club in the future.
同学们 以后我们的读书会
It is important to recommend it.
就要重点推荐
Let everyone read more books on Marxism.
让大家多读马克思主义的书
寿昌先生.
守常先生
sir.
先生
Runzhi and I want to ask you something.
润之和我有件事情想向您请教
You said.
你说
Here's the thing, Mr Shouchang .
是这样的守常先生
I just received a letter from Hunan.
我刚刚收到一封从湖南寄来的信
I think this letter is particularly reasonable.
我觉得这信中讲得特别有道理
So I wanted to come and discuss a solution with you. .
所以呢想过来跟您商量个办法
Please have a look, sir.
先生请您过目
My friend Xiong Guangchu.
我的朋友熊光楚
Is a member of Xinmin Society.
是新民学会的会员
He suggested in the letter.
他在信中啊 建议
It is first promoted by teachers and students of various colleges and universities.
由各个高校的师生首先推动
In towns and villages across the country.
在全国各个乡镇
Generally set up reading rooms. .
普遍设立阅书报室
Carry out a new culture to the people of the whole country. .
以向全国的民众进行新文化
And the propaganda of advanced ideas.
和先进思想的宣传
Gradually improve the quality of the people.
逐步地提高国民的素质
sir.
先生
I think Runzhi's suggestion is particularly good.
我觉得润之这个建议特别地好
Now the enlightenment of new culture thought.
现在新文化思想启蒙
Mainly among students and young people.
主要是在学生和青年之中
If we can set up a reading room .
如果我们能通过设立阅书报室
To gradually improve the quality of the people.
来逐步提高民众素质
Publicize new ideology and culture.
宣传新思想文化
This is a wonderful thing.
这是一件再好不过的事情了
Although the suggestion is good .
建议虽好
But in all towns and villages across the country.
但是要在全国各个乡镇
It's not easy to set up a reading room. .
都设立阅书报室可不容易啊
Mr. Shouchang, this needs at least.
守常先生 这至少需要
Someone should come out and take the lead first. .
有人先出来带个头才行啊
This new culture is going to the public.
这倒是新文化走向大众的
A good suggestion.
一个好建议
But this proposal.
但是这个建议
Will consume a lot of manpower and financial resources. .
会耗去大量的人力和财力
The key, Runzhi, is as you said.
关键正如润之你说的那样
Who will hold this head?
谁来牵这个头
Runzhi's suggestion is.
润之的建议是
Our Peking University will take the lead.
由我们北大来牵这个头
Spreading the new culture is the responsibility of Peking University.
传播新文化 北大当仁不让
But this thing.
但是这件事
You should report it to Mr. Cai. .
应该跟蔡先生汇报一下
Let him decide.
让他来做定夺
OK, I'll write to Mr. Cai now.
好那我现在就给蔡先生写信
good.
好
sir.
先生
classmates.
同学们
I've been thinking about a problem recently. .
我最近一直在想一个问题
Our book club.
我们读书会
You can't just stop at the ideological confrontation.
不能光停留在思想交锋上
More importantly.
更重要的是
Combine truth with practice.
把道理跟践行结合起来
So I have an initiative.
所以我有一个倡议
Set up a work-study mutual aid society.
成立一个半工半读的互助社
According to the theory of mutual aid.
按照互助论的理论
Form a mutual aid group.
组成一个互助式团体
Try out mutual assistance communism.
试行互助式的共产主义
I wonder if you agree.
不知各位是否赞同
Yannian your idea before.
延年之前你这个想法
Wang Guangqi mentioned it.
王光祈就提过
I think there is nothing wrong in theory.
我是觉得理论上没有错
But the actual operation.
不过 实际操作起来
Will it be difficult?
难度会不会很大
I discussed this problem with him.
我跟他讨论过这个问题
He wants to make a big one.
他想弄一个规模大的
But it's also difficult. .
但是那个难度也大呀
I just want to do a small-scale experiment first.
我就是想先做一个小范围的试验
It's in our book club and French study hall.
就在咱们读书会和法文进修馆
Try this range first.
这个范围内先试一试
Today, I just make an initiative first.
我今天就是先做一个倡议
If everyone thinks it's feasible .
要是大家都觉得可行
Then I'll go back to draft the articles of association immediately.
那我马上回去起草章程
He advocates this.
他这个提倡啊
You did a good job.
就做得不错
This is the case and this is the case. .
是这样 也是这样
I think it's pretty good.
我觉得挺不错的
I'm willing to have a try.
我愿意一试
right.
对
I think it's very good to prolong this initiative.
我觉得延年这个倡议非常好
Combining truth with practice.
道理与践行相结合
I have an initiative.
我有个倡议
please.
请
I think the new culture should go to the public.
我认为新文化要走向大众
Must be combined with the masses of workers and peasants.
必须要与工农大众相结合
I did research in Changxindian a while ago.
前些阵子我在长辛店做调研
Also gained a lot.
也收获很多
Xindian has nearly 4,000 workers.
长辛店工人近四千人
Workers work long hours. .
工人工作时间长
Pay less.
工钱却少
Everyone works about ten o'clock every summer.
每人每天夏天约工作十时
Work about 11: 00 or 12: 00 in winter.
冬天约工作十一二时
But the wages only range from three cents to one yuan.
工钱却只有三毛到一元不等
Many workers work all day.
很多工人都是终日劳作
Without food and clothing.
却不得温饱
What surprises me even more is that.
更令我吃惊的是
The number of illiterate workers.
工人中的文盲数量
We took two hundred copies of New Youth.
我们带去两百本 《新青年》
Even the last half was not sold.
最后连一半都没有卖到
I really feel that we are interested in this group.
我真的觉得我们对这个群体
I really don't understand.
实在是太不了解了
So I'm ready to organize with ZhongJie.
所以我跟仲解准备组织
Civilian education lecture group.
平民教育讲演团
Make a series of speeches with Changxindian as a pilot.
以长辛店为试点做系列演讲
And do an in-depth investigation.
并做深入调查
Shiyan is absolutely right.
世炎说得非常对
I think research and speeches.
我是觉得调研和演讲
Should be combined.
应该结合起来
This form of speech.
演讲这种形式
It may be even more urgent for civilians.
可能对于平民来说更加地迫切
Because there are few civilians who can read now. .
因为现在平民当中能识字的人少
People who can read publications and printed matter.
能够阅读出版物 印刷品的人
Even less.
就更少
So if you want to carry out universal education.
所以如果想进行普及教育
You have to start with a speech.
必须先从演讲开始
And I think.
而且我是觉得
The organizational form of this lecture group on civilian education.
这种平民教育讲演团的组织形式
It doesn't have to be complicated.
也不必复杂
You can work in groups of several people.
可以几个人为一组
Draw up a topic in advance.
事先拟好题目
Go to a place where there are many people.
专门去人多的地方
Such as temple fairs, to give speeches. .
比如庙会这种地方去进行演讲
right.
对
The topic doesn't have to be complicated.
讲题也不必复杂
Let's start with common sense of life and current news.
我们从生活常识和新闻时事讲起
We're going to make.
我们要让
Working and poor workers and civilians.
般劳苦贫寒的工人平民
To get a glimpse of current events.
能够借此略知些时事
Learn some common sense.
得知些常识
Then you can realize your position.
继而能意识到自己的地位
And the source of social diseases.
和社会的病源
Let them do some active activities.
再让他们做出些积极的活动来
That won't achieve our goal.
那这可不就达到咱们的目的了嘛
I've been in Changsha these years.
这些年啊我在长沙
Soak among ordinary people every day.
天天泡在普通的民众之中
Their suffering.
他们的苦
Their joy.
他们的乐
I feel the same way more or less.
我多多少少都感同身受
And, ah.
而且啊
I know better what they really want. .
我比较了解他们到底想要的是什么
So Shiyan still has a proposal to prolong life.
所以 世炎还有延年的提议
I couldn't agree more.
我非常赞同
These two societies.
这两个社团
I want to participate.
我都想参加
I participate.
我参加
join.
参加
Yannian.
延年
You asked me just now.
你刚才问我
What do you think of your proposal?
觉得你那个倡议怎么样
I want to applaud you and Shiyan.
我想给你还有世炎鼓鼓掌
classmates.
同学们
Why should I applaud these two students?
我为什么要给这二位同学鼓掌
Because these two students.
因为这二位同学
They all saw a problem.
都不约而同地看到了一个问题
That is, theory and practice should be combined.
那就是理论和实际要结合起来
It's like we're celebrating.
这个就像我们在庆祝
As stated at the European War Victory Conference.
欧战胜利大会上讲的那样
New Culture Movement.
新文化运动
Now we have reached a turning point.
现在已经到了一个转折点
That turning point is the New Culture Movement. .
那这个转折点就是新文化运动
Go to the public.
要走向大众
Nakasuke.
仲解
There is an echo of the letter to Mr. Ercai.
尔给蔡先生的信有回音了
What did Mr Cai say?
蔡先生怎么说
Mr Cai fully supports it.
蔡先生全力支持
And urge us all.
而且督促我们大家
Go out as soon as possible.
要尽快走出去
I have just listened to your classmates' speeches.
刚才听了诸位同学的发言
I am both excited and admired.
我是既兴奋 又钦佩
Excited is that.
兴奋的是
I saw everyone's insights.
我看到了大家的真知灼见
Admire that.
钦佩的是
I saw everyone's pioneering spirit.
我看到了大家的开拓精神
You choose to go out.
你们选择要走出去
That means giving up a lot.
那就意味着要放弃很多
It means that you have chosen a difficult road.
意味着你们选择了一条困难之路
And gave up a comfortable Shizhi road.
而放弃了一条舒适之路
It means that you have chosen a pioneering road.
意味着你们选择了一条开拓之路
And gave up a road to success.
而放弃了一条守成之路
It means that you have chosen one.
意味着你们选择了一条
The road to struggle against difficulties.
迎着困难而上的拼搏之路
And gave up the comfortable road of sitting and talking. .
而放弃了坐而论道的安逸之路
classmates.
同学们
We are going out of the study soon.
我们马上要走出书斋
Go to the grass-roots level.
走向基层了
I know this road is hard and bitter.
我知道这条路很难 很苦
But I firmly believe.
但是我坚信
No matter how hard it is.
再难再苦的路
Can't beat you either.
也难不倒诸位
Because I saw everyone's courage.
因为我看到了大家的勇气
Boys and girls, I sincerely hope that everyone.
同学们我真心希望大家
Be able to step on the dirt with both feet.
能够双脚踩在泥土里
length by length.
一步一步地
Get down to .
踏踏实实地
Take every step of the way.
走好每一步路
And I believe that victory will definitely belong to us. .
而且我相信胜利一定会属于我们
Because we're already on our way.
因为我们已经在路上了
good.
好
Let's solve a problem.
我们解决一个问题
We must first know the essence of this problem.
必先认识这个问题的本质
Then this is the purpose of going to the grass-roots level.
那么走入基层 就是这个目的
It's just that trees are expensive today.
正好今天树贵
We made appointments with many workers' representatives.
帮我们约了很多的工人代表
Be sure to ask questions. .
一定要好好提问
Only when there are problems will there be knowledge.
有问题才会有认识
Sir, Mr. Shouchang.
先生 守常先生
sir.
先生
润之仲解.
润之 仲解
寿昌先生.
守常先生
来了润之.
来了润之
I'll ask Zhong Jie to call you here.
我让仲解把你叫过来
I want to invite you to participate in our activities in Peking University.
是想邀请你参加我们北大的活动
I'm not bothering you, am I?
没有打扰你吧
no.
没有 没有
How long has Runzhi been in Beijing?
润之 来北京多长时间了
It's been more than half a year.
有半年多了
Have you ever been to Changxindian?
去过长辛店吗
I've been to Zhong Jie and Zhao Shiyan.
跟仲解 还有赵世炎去过一趟
But it's all a cursory visit.
但都是走马观花
I know you are going to do special research this time.
这次知道您要去做专题的调研
Opportunities are (like angels' visits) few and far between.
机会难得
I can also get a closer look. .
我呢 也可以近距离地了解一下
The state of workers.
工人的状态
Marx said.
马克思说过
Industrial working class.
产业工人阶级
Is the most advanced class in the world.
是全世界最先进的阶级
But this sentence.
但是这句话
Is it in line with China's reality?
是否符合中国的实际
I think it's a real problem.
我认为还真是一个现实的问题
We have been to Changxindian several times before.
我们之前去过长辛店几次
I think Marx has a point.
我觉得马克思说得有道理
Makes no sense.
有没有道理
Let us experience it with our own heart.
需要让我们自己用心去体会
You are in charge of recording today.
今天你负责记录吧
good.
好
This is for the guests.
这是给客人准备的
Go play.
玩去吧
Please come in, please.
请进 请进 请进
everyone.
各位
This is the one I always tell you about.
这位啊就是我经常给你们提起来的
Professor Li Dazhao of Peking University .
北京大学的李大钊李教授
Hello, masters.
各位师傅好
These guys.
这几位啊
It's Professor Li's students.
是李教授的学生们
Mr. Dazhao, sit down.
大钊先生 坐
Sit, sit.
坐坐坐
Excuse me, masters.
打扰了啊 各位师傅
Sit inside, sit inside.
里边坐 里边坐
Come by yourself.
自己来吧
Thank you.
谢谢 谢谢
You're welcome.
不用不用 您客气了
Polite.
客气客气
Sit down, sit down.
您坐坐坐
Professor Li, come on.
李教授他们来啊
Just wanted to ask us.
就是想问问咱们啊
Is there any difficulty?
有没有什么难处
Have a chat with us.
跟咱们聊聊天
Professor Li, these.
李教授 这些啊
It's all the old workers on our railway.
都是咱们铁路上的老工发
Please feel free to ask if you have any questions. .
您有什么问题 尽管问
good.
好
Hello, masters.
各位师傅们好
To this gentleman.
给这位先生
Actually, we're here.
其实我们这趟来啊
Just want to talk to the masters.
就是想跟各位师傅们
Chat and talk.
聊聊天 谈谈心
Everyone knows that.
大家也都知道
This world war is over.
这个世界大战结束了
China, on the other hand, has become a victorious country.
我们中国呢 成为了战胜国
But we in China.
可是我们中国
How did you become a victorious country?
是怎么成为战胜国的呢
That's because of China.
那就是因为我们中国啊
Sent more than a dozen workers.
派了十几方的劳工
Went to the European battlefield.
去了欧洲战场
Because of these workers.
正是因为这些劳工
With one's own blood, sweat and life.
用自己的血汗和生命
Come to our country.
来为了我们这个国家
Won the honor!
争得了这份荣誉啊
Personally, I also think.
我个人也认为
Our Chinese workers.
我们中国的劳工
Is the most hardworking person in the world.
是这个世界上最勤劳
The greatest worker.
最伟大的劳工
Should be widely respected by the society.
理应得到社会的广泛尊重
Professor Li.
李教授
Ah, you're welcome.
您啊就别客气了
If you have any questions, just ask.
有什么问题啊您尽管问
We don't hide anything.
我们呢也不藏着掖着的
Okay, okay, okay.
好好好
I want to ask you a question first. .
我想先问各位师傅一个问题
What specific jobs are you engaged in?
大家都是从事哪些具体工作的
Xindian locomotive and rolling stock factory.
长辛店机车车辆厂
It is an early modern industry in China.
是中国早期的近代工业
It belonged to China's early industrial army. .
是中国早期产业大军的
Important breeding ground.
重要孕育地之
After the October Revolution in Russia.
俄国十月革命后
Chinese advanced elements are beginning to realize .
中国先进分子开始意识到
The great power of the working class.
工人阶级蕴藏的巨大力量
March 1919.
一九一九年三月
Unde that guidance of Li Dazhao.
在李大钊指导下
Organized and established in Peking University in Deng Zhongxia. .
邓中夏在北京大学组织建立
Civilian education lecture group.
平民教育讲演团
Start giving lectures at Changxindian.
开始到长辛店开展讲演活动
In the process of integrating with the masses of workers .
在与工人群众相结合的过程中
Li Dazhao, Deng Zhongxia and others.
李大钊 邓中夏等一批
Preliminary contact.
初步接触了
Marxist intellectuals.
马克思主义的知识分子
Thoughts and feelings are further transformed into.
思想感情进一步转变到
On the working class side.
工人阶级方面来
At the same time, some workers such as Ge Shugui.
同时 葛树贵等一部分工人
Thanks to the education of Marxism-Leninism.
由于受到马克思列宁主义的教育
And improve class consciousness.
而提高阶级觉悟
Become an advanced member of the working class.
成为工人阶级的先进分子
Shiyan, do you know anything about the countryside?
世炎你了解农村吗
My family has been studying since childhood in the town.
我家在镇上 打小就读书
I really don't know much about the countryside.
对农村还真不怎么了解
I think in our country.
我觉得 在咱们国家
Workers live like farmers.
工人和农民生活差不多
Not much difference.
没多少区别
How can you see it that way?
怎么会这么看
I think if I want to understand China .
我觉得 要想了解中国
First of all, we must understand farmers. .
首先就要了解农民
寿昌先生.
守常先生
I have a question I want to ask you.
我有一个疑虑 想请教您
You said.
你说
I always thought.
我以前一直觉得
The image of industrial workers in our country is particularly tall.
咱们国家的产业工人形象特别高大
But why?
可为什么
Their life is so hard.
他们的生活也如此艰苦啊
This is China's national condition.
这就是中国国情
And the differences between Japan and even Europe.
和日本乃至欧洲国情的差别
Although I have never been abroad, I know.
我虽然没有出过国 但是我知道
The industrialization level of our country.
我们国家的工业化水平
There is no comparison with them.
跟他们是没的比的
Revolution in Europe.
在欧洲的革命
Are held with the working class as the center.
都是以工人阶级为中心举行
Biru said Paris commune.
你比如说巴黎公社
Russian October Revolution.
俄国的十月革命
Are centered on the working class.
都是以工人阶级为中心
Held in the central city.
以中心城市举行的
Working class in Europe.
在欧洲 工人阶级
Is the most conscious and disciplined.
是最有觉悟 最讲纪律
The most united class. .
最团结的一个阶层
I think the workers in our country are not simple either. .
我觉得咱们国家的工人也不简单
Although they are not highly educated.
虽然他们文化程度不太高
I've had a hard time.
日子呢 过得也苦
But they have no interest in our country.
但是他们对于咱们的国家
Still very concerned.
还是很关心的
Some of their words touched me very much today.
今天他们有些话 就很令我感动
It's raining.
下雨了
Let's go to the tea shop in front to take shelter from the rain. .
咱们去前面茶铺避避雨吧
good.
好
The hill came to shelter from the rain.
小山 来避避雨
a good man.
好先生
Hurry up, hurry up!
快点快点快点
What a heavy rain!
好大的雨啊
Lao ban lai Hu cha .
老板来壶茶
Ah, guys.
几位啊
Five people.
五个人
Okay, okay, okay.
好好好
Come in for shelter after the hill is busy.
小山 忙活好了之后进来避雨啊
a good man.
好 先生
Come, sir, please.
来先生请
Nakasuke.
仲解
Actually, I just felt the same way as you.
其实我刚才的感觉 跟你一样
Ah, just workers in our country.
只是啊我们国家的工人
It's too little.
实在是太少了
And what I didn't expect was that.
而且令我没有想到的是
There are also many workers who came from bankrupt farmers.
还有很多的工人是破产农民出身
Although their lifestyle has changed.
他们的生活方式虽然发生了改变
But the circumstances of this life.
但这生活的境况
Without any change.
却没有任何的变化
Even some people are worse than before.
甚至有些人还不如以前呢
Ah, so their mode of thinking and way of thinking.
所以啊他们的思维模式和思考方式
It's the same as before. It doesn't make much difference.
都和以前一样 没有多大区别
I think for a real revolution.
我认为 要想真正的革命
First of all, we should start with farmers.
首先就要从农民着手
Runzhi, that's a good question.
润之这个问题提得好啊
I think we should find a way out for China.
我觉得我们要为中国寻找出路
This problem should be studied. .
应该研究这个问题
Jiewo Marquez Research Institute.
仲解我们马尔克斯研究会
To study this problem.
要研究这个问题
Sir, there's one more thing that shocked me today. .
先生 今天还有一点让我特别震惊
That is the number of illiterate workers in Changxindian.
那就是长辛店工人文盲的数量
It is beyond my imagination.
实在是超乎我的想象
I remembered the letter from Xiong Guangchu.
我想起了熊光楚同学的那封来信
His letter mentioned above .
他那封信上面提到
It's too important to talk about civilian education.
说平民教育实在是太重要了
So I think.
所以我觉得
We should send the public education lecture group as soon as possible.
我们应该尽快把平民教育讲演团
organize.
组织起来
Sir, do you think.
先生您觉得
Where should we start first?
我们应该先从哪方面入手呢
Don't we have a red chamber reading club at Peking University?
咱们北大不是有红楼读书会吗
That's actually a youth evening school.
那个实际上就是青年夜校
I think we can start an evening school for workers.
我觉得我们可以开办一个工人夜校
Let's put the education of the workers on campus first.
先把校内工人的教育问题
Make it up first.
先搞起来
Then gradually spread to the whole society.
然后逐步逐步推广到全社会
A good idea is easy before it is difficult.
好主意 先易后难
in addition.
另外
We can be led by several publications.
我们可以由几个刊物来牵头
For example, "National" and "Trendy".
比如说 《国民》 《新潮》
Weekly Review and New Youth.
《每周评论》 还有 《新青年》
This solves the problem of our teachers.
这样就解决了我们师资
There is also the question of funding.
还有经费问题
Well, let's discuss it tonight. .
好那今天晚上我们就去讨论
good.
好
No less.
都没少
all right.
可以了
Then I said it.
那我说了啊
right.
对
good.
好
Listen to me, everybody. .
大家听我说一下啊
Today, by putting Guo Xingang.
今天借着把郭心刚
There are two people Liu Haiwei.
还有刘海威两个人
The opportunity to come from Peking University.
从北大请过来的机会
Let's read the general rules of mutual aid society.
咱们大家把工读互助社简章
Negotiate.
商议一下
There are three articles in the general rules of the Mutual Aid Society.
工读互助社简章一共是三条
Let me read it to you.
我给大家念一下啊
The first member is each person per day.
第一 社员每日每人
Must work for four hours. .
必须工作四个小时
2. Necessary food, clothing and accommodation for members.
第二 社员必需之衣食住
Supplied by groups.
由团体供给
Education fees and books fees required by members .
社员所需之教育费书籍费
Books must be owned by groups.
准书籍归团体公有
Third, the income from work is owned by the group.
第三工作所得归团体公有
Do you have anything to add? .
各位还有什么需要补充的吗
I think.
我认为啊
We should be in the brief. .
我们应当在简章中
Declare clearly.
旗帜鲜明地宣布
Gongdu Mutual Aid Society.
工读互助社
It is implemented according to the theory of mutual aid. .
是根据互助论的理论实行的
Communism without any constraints.
没有任何约束的共产主义
Lao Guo, that's a good point. .
老郭这条提得好
I agree.
我同意啊
Wait a minute.
稍微等一下啊
Since mutual aid societies practice communism.
既然互助社实行共产主义
Then I think.
那么我认为
All members should explicitly.
所有的社员都应当明确地
Break away from family relations and marriage relations .
脱离家庭关系和婚姻关系
What do you think is the relationship between members?
那你认为社员之间是什么关系
Can everything be exchanged for what one needs? .
难道什么都可以互通有无吗
No, Prynne, you misunderstood.
不白兰你误会了
I mean, between members.
我是说 社员之间
It should be a gay relationship.
应该是同志的关系
It's thought and property.
是思想上和财产上
A completely accommodating relationship.
完全通融的关系
What about this gay relationship?
这种同志关系呢
Should not be affected by family. .
不应该受家庭
Crane of school and marriage.
学校和婚姻的鹤
What do you mean by that?
你这话什么意思啊
Do you want to get out of touch with your family?
难道要跟家里脱离关系吗
This is so unreasonable.
这太不通情达理了
Is this necessary?
有这个必要吗
It is necessary.
有这个必要
No laborer can eat.
不劳动者不得食
This is the most basic principle of communism.
这是共产主义一个最基本的原则
We have to rely on our own hands.
我们就是要靠自己的双手
Feed themselves.
养活自己
Create the world.
创造世界
Instead of relying on parents and families.
而不是依靠父母跟家庭
Are you going to break up with your parents in Chen Yannian? .
陈延年 你要跟父母断绝关系吗
Not to break up with my parents.
不是要跟父母断绝关系
But to sever economic ties with the family.
而是要跟家庭断绝经济关系
After joining the club.
入社以后
Don't let your family send you any more money.
不要让家里再给你寄钱了
Can you do it?
能做到吗
I can do it.
我能做到
I'll write a letter to my family in a couple of days.
我这两天就给家里写封信吧
Brother, are we.
哥那咱们是不是
Can't go home for dinner either.
也不能回家吃饭啦
Let me talk about this question.
这个问题我说一下
Not only can't we all go home for dinner.
我们大家不仅不能回家吃饭
You can't eat at school either.
也不能在学校吃饭
This meal doesn't count. Keep eating.
这顿不算你们接着吃
We want to run our own canteen.
我们要办自己的食堂
Eat a big pot of rice and wear big clothes.
吃大锅饭 穿大家衣
Great.
太好了
What am I going to do for everyone?
我来给大伙做哪
My father is the cook of Shandong Shandong Shandong Restaurant.
我父亲 著名山东鲁菜馆的厨子
But I got the true biography.
我可是得到真传了
Braised sea cucumber with onion is our unique skill.
葱烧海参 那可是咱的绝活
Give Liu Haiwei a high hand.
给刘海威鼓个掌
good.
好
Then let's go down and get ready.
那大家就下去各自准备吧
go.
走
Furong cake.
芙蓉糕
Cake Lama.
喇嘛糕
Deep-fried dumplings with fried seeds .
油炸烩子炸元宵
I have read the report.
报告我已经看了
Civilian education itself is .
平民教育本身是
An important part of the new culture movement.
新文化运动的一个重要内容
Education has been popularized.
教育普及了
To spread the new culture.
新文化才能传播下去
So the lecture group is good.
所以讲演团也好
Work-study mutual aid society is also good.
工读互助社也好
It is a practice base.
它就是个实践基地
It is also a sign that we are going to the people.
也是我们走向民众的一个标志
I totally agree.
我完全同意
Great, Mr. Cai.
太好了 蔡先生
Actually, I discussed this matter with brother Zhongfu.
其实这件事我和仲甫兄商量过
We are looking for someone to raise funds from the society. .
我们想找人向社会募集资金
Besides, the Weekly Review.
另外《每周评论》啊
New Youth.
《新青年》啊
Also open up projects.
也要开辟项目
Guide these two activities at the same time.
同时指导这两项活动
I have an uninvited invitation here. .
我这儿有一个不情之请啊
Mr. Cai.
蔡先生
You said.
你说
To raise funds from the society.
向社会募集资金的事
You have to take the lead.
还得由您来牵头才行啊
It's my duty to take the lead.
责无旁贷 我来牵头
Great.
太好了
In addition, I suggest that the public education lecture group .
另外 我建议平民教育讲演团
We should start with Peking University.
应该先从北大做起
Start with the janitor of Peking University.
先从北大的校工开始做起
Easy before difficult 1.
先易后难1
Easy before difficult.
先易后难
Then gradually expand to the whole society.
然后逐步扩大到全社会
good.
好
Come up with a plan.
拿出个方案来
What's the difficulty in getting ZhongfuShizhi to help?
有什么困难 让仲甫适之帮忙
They will certainly support it.
他们一定会支持的
good.
好
aunt.
姨妈
what's up.
怎么了
Yannian qiaonian.
延年乔年
Why did you come back so late?
你们怎么这么晚才回来啊
What's going on here?
这是怎么回事
Nothing happened.
没怎么回事
By the way, why did you come back so late?
对了 你们怎么这么晚才回来
Tell the truth.
您说实话
南卡罗来纳州.
SC
How many times has this happened?
这种情况到底出现多少次了
Not many times.
没多少次
Just once.
就一次
Just this time.
就这一次
Last time, tabloids were delivered directly to home.
上次小报都直接送到家里
Don't mention that last time.
上次那个事就别提了
Does he know?
他知道吗
He still doesn't care, does he.
他还是不管是吗
How does he manage?
他怎么管
Your father has so much.
你爸爸手上有这么多
Important things to do.
重要的事情要做
Yannian.
延年
The wise man knows he knows nothing.
清者自清
a person standing straight doesn't worry about his shadow slanting—an upright person fears no gossip.
身正不怕影子斜
You must remember this sentence.
这句话你一定要记住
done.
好了
Nothing. Come on.
没事来
Go home with menstruation.
跟姨妈回家
come.
来
It's okay to go.
走 没事
It's okay.
没事走
go.
走
Come into the house.
来进屋
中富.
仲甫
Come and help wash it. .
你来帮着洗呀
Yannian and Qiao Nian are back.
延年和乔年回来了
Brother Qiao Nian.
乔年哥哥
Why are you back so late? .
怎么回来这么晚啊
Are you at home?
您在家呀
Ah, rare.
难得啊
Where am I going when I'm not at home? .
我不在家去哪儿啊
Didn't clean you.
没洗干净你
Liumei didn't come back with you. .
柳眉没跟你们一块回来啊
She is writing a letter to her family at school.
她在学校给家里写信呢
Homesick.
想家了
Not homesick.
不是想家
I'm writing a letter to sever ties with my family.
是在写给家里断绝关系的信
disengage.
断绝关系
What's the matter?
出什么事了吗
Nothing happened.
没出什么事
Let's come this time.
我们这次来
Is also out of relationship with you.
也是跟你们脱离关系的
Get out of touch with us.
跟我们脱离关系
Dad, menstruation.
爸 姨妈
Let me read our statement with you.
我跟你们读一下我们的声明
Chen Yannian Voluntary Organization.
陈延年陈乔年自愿组织
And join the work-study mutual aid society.
并加入工读互助社
Practice mutual aid theory.
践行互助论
Implement communism.
实行共产主义
From now on .
从即日起
Break away from all economic relations with the family.
与家庭脱离一切经济关系
And the associated responsibilities and obligations.
以及所连带的责任和义务
Hereby declare.
特此声明
Get along while.
搞了半天
Just to start this support group?
你们就为了搞这个互助社
Just like my father menstruation.
就要跟父亲 姨妈
And my younger brothers and sisters have broken up. .
还有弟弟妹妹们断了关系啊
What kind of support society is this? .
这哪是什么互助社嘛
It's called "No Six Parents Club", okay?
这叫六亲不认社好吗
Menstruation, you misunderstood.
姨妈 您误会了
We're not breaking away from blood relations. .
我们不是要脱离血亲关系
We want to get rid of economic ties.
我们是要撇清经济连带关系
start from today.
从今天开始
Joe and I can't spend our family money.
我和乔年就不能花家里的钱了
Can't go home for dinner. .
也不能回家吃饭
We have to support ourselves.
我们要自己养活自己
Because we are communist.
因为我们共产了
communist.
共产
Isn't this a child playing house?
这不是小孩子过家家吗
中富.
仲甫
you.
你
Did you wipe them?
是不是你擦摄他们弄的呀
Take the children to bed. .
带小孩子去睡觉
Yannian qiaonian.
延年乔年
Come here.
你们过来
sit.
坐
Let's go to bed.
我们睡觉去来
let's talk about.
我们聊聊
go.
走
Go to sleep with your mother.
跟妈妈睡觉去
What is divorce, mom? .
妈妈 什么是脱离关系
Children don't ask this.
小孩子不要问这个
Hurry up and go to sleep!
赶紧睡觉
come.
来
The reason why I want to have a serious talk with you.
我之所以要跟你们郑重地谈一下
Because you are now.
是因为你们现在
What is important is not trivial. .
要做的事不是小事
You are not on a whim.
你们不是一时心血来潮
You are doing an experiment.
你们在做一种实验
but.
但是
You should be prepared for failure.
你们要做好失败的心理准备
I wasn't prepared for that.
我可没这准备
I won't fail.
我不会失败的
Self-confidence is an advantage.
自信是优点
But you can't be blind and confident.
但不能盲自自信
I'm not blind.
我没盲目啊
I'm using the most advanced theory as a guide. .
我在用最先进的理论做指导
There are many theories popular in Europe now.
现在欧洲流行很多种理论
What makes you say anarchism?
你凭什么说无政府主义
Is the advanced theory.
就是先进的理论
I don't get it.
这我就闹不明白了
Didn't you also say.
你不是也说过
Is anarchism a good doctrine?
无政府主义是好主义吗
I think anarchism has good things.
我认为无政府主义有好的东西
But advocate more experiments.
但主张多实验
To test it in the experiment.
要在实验中检验它
I want to remind you.
我是想提醒你
This kind of experiment.
这种实验
You may pay a huge price.
可能你会付出巨大的代价
Because it may not conform to our national conditions.
因为它未必符合我们的国情
I'm against anarchism.
我对无政府主义
I've been tracking it for years. .
跟踪研究好几年了
I trust my own judgment.
我相信我自己的判断力
Anarchist mutual aid theory.
无政府主义的互助论
Can save China.
是能够救中国的
Advanced scientific theory.
先进的科学理论
What theory is the most advanced? .
什么理论最先进
What theory is most suitable for China?
什么理论最适合中国
This is to compare and experiment.
这要比较和实验
Can't jump to conclusions.
不能妄下结论
I support you because you are doing it.
我支持你 因为你在做
But some people are empty talkers.
可是有一些人是空谈主义
Don't listen blindly.
不要盲目听信
Who are you?
你指谁啊
Like Wu Zhihui.
比如吴稚晖
You say me, you say me. .
你说我就说我
What are you doing with someone else for no reason? .
你平白扯上别人干什么呀
Why can't I say him?
我为什么不能说他
I'm going to talk about him today.
我今天就要说他
He sings high all day.
他整天唱高调
Dress yourself up as a virtuous saint.
把自己打扮成良德的圣人
Deceive young people to be his followers.
欺骗年轻人做他的信徒
Once you don't believe him .
一旦你不信他了
This kind of person turns his face when he says he turns his face. .
这种人说翻脸就翻脸
You can't get too close to him.
你不能跟他接触得太近
You have to be careful.
你要留点心眼才行
You didn't fall out.
您也没少翻脸
Should I also keep an eye on you?
我是不是也该对您留个心眼
By the way, you are not turned against.
对了 您也不算翻脸
Because you just wore a fake face.
因为您直接就戴了个假脸
You support it in your mouth, but you don't agree with it in your heart.
你嘴上支持 心里却不认同
A duplicity is a falsehood.
口是心非为假
Because of your personal words and deeds.
因为你个人的言行
Bring so much trouble to the family.
给家里带来这么大的麻烦
But as if nothing had happened, it was also false.
却若无其事也是假
What qualifications do you have for a man like you? .
像你这样的人你有什么资格
Speak of others on a moral level. .
站在道德的高度上说别人
I am sharing my life experience with you.
我在用我的人生经验与你共勉
Why are you so resistant? .
你为什么要这么抗拒呢
I'm telling you something serious.
我在跟你说正经事
Why do you say these asshole words?
你为什么要说这些浑蛋的话
I'm also talking about something serious. .
我也在说正经事
I didn't do anything stupid.
可我没干浑蛋事
What are you doing?
干吗你这是
I thought I told you to talk well.
不是让你好好说话吗
brother.
哥
Yannian.
延年
More sauce.
多点酱
Since I came to Beijing.
我自从来了北京啊
I've never eaten this before.
就没吃过这个
Give me a hand.
来帮我一下
a slap in the face .
真香
come.
来
Try.
尝尝
No.
香不
Hot.
好辣
My heart just returned these to me every day.
心刚 天天拿这些填还我
What is Ann's heart?
到底安的什么心啊
What do you mean, return it to you?
什么叫填还你啊
It's called pancake roll with green onions.
这叫煎饼卷大葱
The more you eat, the stronger you are.
越吃越有劲
The more energetic.
越有劲
Yannian.
延年
Why are you back?
你怎么回来了
I'm really sorry.
实在对不住啊
I thought you weren't coming back tonight. .
我以为你今天晚上不回来了
These are my fellow villagers in Qingdao. .
这些都是我青岛的一些老乡
It's too late today, so stay here for the night. .
今天太晚了 就在这里借宿一宿
it doesn't matter.
没事
What are they doing here?
他们是来做什么的
To petition.
来请愿的
Ask the government to take back Qingdao occupied by Germany. .
要求政府收回被德国占领的青岛
This also brought a discount for all people.
这还带了万民折
That's a big deal.
那这是大事
You live here in a down-to-earth manner.
你们在这儿踏踏实实住
I went to Zhao Shiyan to pour my leg.
我找赵世炎倒腿去了
Yannian.
延年
You come.
你来
Come here.
你过来
Let me introduce you.
我给你介绍一下
This is my cousin Guo Xinyi.
这是我堂弟郭心义
And the leader of this petition group.
也是这次请愿团的头儿
That's what I always tell you.
这就是我跟你经常说的
Mr. Chen Duxiu's eldest son Chen Yannian.
陈独秀先生的长子陈延年
Rely on Chen Tongxue .
仰仗陈同学了
hello.
你好
Yannian.
延年
You have to help with this.
这事你得帮忙
They are all students.
他们都是学生
Ganglai.
刚来
Where are petitions sent again and again?
连连请愿书往哪儿送
I don't even know.
都不知道呢
Don't be polite to me. .
你就别跟我客气了
I am duty-bound to do this.
这事我责无旁贷
I'm going to put Mao Zedong.
这样 我去把毛泽东
And Zhao Shiyan, they called over. .
还有赵世炎他们叫过来
Let's discuss how to do this together.
咱们一块商量一下这事怎么办
Okay, okay, that's a good idea.
好好好这个主意好
Then let's go now.
那咱俩现在就去
go.
走
Prynne, please say hello.
白兰 你招呼一下啊
Leave it to me.
放心交给我
come.
来
I wronged everyone today.
今天就委屈大家
Make do here for a night.
在这儿凑合一宿了
Sir, these are my fellow villagers.
先生这几位都是我的老乡
Just came to Beijing yesterday. .
昨天刚来北京
I don't know where to send the petition.
不知道请愿书往哪儿送
Just came to Peking University for help.
才来北大求援的
We spent the whole night last night.
昨天晚上我们合计了一晚上
I still have to trouble you, sir. Do something about it. .
这事还得麻烦先生您给想想办法
寿昌先生.
守常先生
We are entrusted by Shandong people.
我们受山东民众的委托
Come to Beijing to submit a petition and a universal discount.
来北京递交请愿书和万民折
But this is our first time in Beijing.
但我们都是第一次来北京
Don't know what to do about it. .
不知道这件事该怎么做
Please ask Mr. Shouchang to give advice and guidance.
还请守常先生能给予点拨和指导
Dialing is far from guidance.
点拨和指导谈不上
This petition of Qingdao petition group.
青岛请愿团的这份请愿书
Not only represents your Qingdao.
不光代表了你们青岛
It also represents all of us Chinese.
也代表了我们全体中国人
A common wish.
共同的心愿
Peking University rightly responded and supported. .
北大理所应当地响应和支持
I'll tell you what, Xingang.
我看这样吧心刚
Go and find some classmates who write well.
你去找一些写字好的同学
Copy dozens of petitions.
把请愿书抄上几十份
Posted in public at Peking University.
在北大的公开场合张贴
It's better to print it as a leaflet.
最好 还能印成传单
Widely distributed.
广泛地印发
Can expand the influence.
可以扩大影响
good.
好
long and slender eyebrows (of a woman).
柳眉
Later, you should go and find Professor Hu Shi. .
一会儿你们去找一趟胡适教授
Please do me a favor.
请他帮个忙
Send the invitation letters to the embassies of Britain, America, France and Italy.
把给英美法意各个使馆的呼请信
Translate into English.
翻译成英文
good.
好
As for the petition, the people call for letters.
至于请愿书 万民折 呼请信
How to send it up? .
怎么送上去
Coincidence.
巧了
We will hold a school meeting later.
一会儿我们要召开个校务会
I'll discuss it with you. .
我跟大家商量一下
Gather the thoughts of all and the power of all. .
集众人之思 众人之力
I believe there will be a good way.
我相信一定会有好的办法的
Can you watch T?
你们看 T 行吗
Thank you, Mr. Shouchang.
谢谢守常先生
史鸷.
适之
Pen.
钢笔毛笔
The typewriters are all here.
打字机都在这儿
No matter which one you use.
不管你用哪个
Articles in the Weekly Review.
《每周评论》 的文章
You have to write it today.
你今天必须得写出来
today.
今天
Must also.
还必须
Isn't that forcing?
那这不强人所难吗
I don't even use it.
我都不用
What's wrong with forcing others?
怎么强人所难了
Look at me so much.
看我这么多事
I'm so busy.
我真忙不过来呀
I ask you.
我问你
Are you a fellow editor of New Youth?
你是不是 《新青年》 的同人编辑
I am.
我是啊
What about the Weekly Review.
那《每周评论》
Is not the top priority of New Youth.
是不是 《新青年》 的重中之重
What's wrong with forcing others?
怎么强人所难了
You want your scoundrel.
你要你的无赖
I won't tell you. I'll check the information.
我不跟你说 我查资料去
It seems that today.
看来今天
You really carried this scoundrel through to the end.
你真把这无赖进行到底啊
You know I'm always afraid of people.
你知道我一向不畏人言
You're a rogue.
就耍无赖了
Isn't this bullying honest people?
这不是欺负老实人吗
Is to bully honest people.
就是要欺负老实人
I'm telling you, honest people like you don't bully.
我告诉你 你这种老实人不欺负
You will always be an honest man.
你永远都是老实人
What logic are you talking about?
你这什么逻辑呀
Hello, Mr. Shizhi.
适之先生好
hello.
你好
We've been spending this afternoon.
我们今天下午一直
Uncle Chen, why are you hiding behind the door?
陈伯伯 您怎么躲到门后啊
never mind.
没事 没事
Chen Bobo is good.
陈伯伯好
Mr. Shizhi is like this.
适之先生 是这样的
These are our four embassies to Britain, France, America and Italy. .
这是我们给英法美意四个使馆
Write a call letter to go back to Qingdao.
写的要回青岛的呼请信
Show me.
给我看一下
It's quite good.
挺好的呀
Very touching.
挺感人的
Brother Zhongfu, take a look.
仲甫兄 你也看看
I don't need to look.
我不用看
It must be good.
一定很好
Because if these four letters.
如果因为这四封信
With the support of these four countries.
得到这四国的支持
It must be of great benefit to recover Qingdao.
那对于收回青岛一定大有碑益
史鸷先生.
适之先生
Mr. Shouchang asked you to translate it into English.
守常先生让您翻译成英文
Let the students of the petition group.
让请愿团的同学
Send it to the legations. .
给各公使馆送过去
It must be finished today.
今天必须翻完
today.
今天
must.
必须
I have another one that must wait for me today.
我这儿还有个今天必须等着我呢
Liumei, like this.
柳眉·这样啊
Uncle Hu also gives you a report.
胡叔叔也给你汇报一下
My latest job.
我最近的工作
My tutor, Professor Dewey.
我的导师杜威教授
I'm going to give lectures in China soon.
马上就要来华讲学了
I want to translate her speech.
我要翻译他的演讲稿
And arrange his schedule.
还要安排他的日程
Arrange the place of his speech and visit.
安排他的演讲地点 考察地点
All right, all right.
行了行了
Shizhi, stop it.
适之 别说了
About Qingdao.
关乎青岛
What are these things to you?
你这些算什么事啊
You can do this job first. .
这样 你先把这活儿干了
This matter cannot be excused.
这事 不容推托
Okay, I'll do Shouchang's thing.
行那守常的事我做
I won't do your business.
你的事我就不做了
What do you mean, I won't do anything? .
什么叫我的事就不做了
Yes first.
是先
Let's do this job first.
先把这活儿干了
Translate this during the day.
白天把这个翻译了
evening.
晚上
Write the article in the Weekly Review.
把《每周评论》 的文章写了
I have to sleep at ten o'clock in the evening.
晚上十点我还得睡觉呢
Before ten.
十点之前
Finish writing.
写完
Go to bed at ten.
十点上床
How good.
多好
Think of me as a donkey.
你把我当成驴了吧
Not a donkey.
不是当驴
Be a camel.
是当骆驼
Okay.
行了
long and slender eyebrows (of a woman).
柳眉
Dumenkou.
堵门口
He won't let him go until he translates it.
他不翻译出来 不让他走
Hangwo translation.
行 我翻译
You really listen to him. .
你还真听他的
What took you so long? .
怎么去了这么久
Wait a minute.
再等会儿
classmates.
同学们
寿昌先生.
守常先生
Good news!
好消息啊
Professors are very concerned about the return of Qingdao.
教授们非常关注青岛的回归问题
Du said.
都表示
Peking University will give its full support.
北京大学一定全力支持
The petition activities of Qingdao petition group .
青岛请愿团的请愿活动
Just now.
就在刚才
Mr. Cai to the chairman of the Foreign Affairs Committee.
蔡先生给外交委员会的委员长
Wang Man spoke by telephone.
汪大慢通了电话
I hope Wang Da can give support.
希望汪大能够给予支持
Wang agreed.
汪大同意
In his office this afternoon.
今天下午在他的办公室
Meet with delegates.
接见各位代表
This is a big note.
这个注大蔓呀
Can be the acting prime minister of the government.
可做过政府的代理国务总理
The diplomatic agency he presided over .
他主持的外交机构
It is the highest diplomatic institution in China.
是中国最高的外交机构
So he intervened.
所以由他出面交涉
i believe.
我相信
Qingdao petition group will surely live up to its mission.
青岛请愿团一定会不辱使命
And our liberal arts senior at Peking University.
而且我们北大的文科学长
Mr Chen Duxiu also said.
陈独秀先生也表示
Fully support the petition activities of Qingdao petition group. .
全力支持青岛请愿团的请愿活动
Not only in New Youth.
不光要在 《新青年》
In the Weekly Review.
《每周评论》上
Publish our petition and call letter.
发表我们的请愿书 呼请信
And publish a series of critical articles.
还要刊登一系列的评论文章
To urge the government to increase the efforts to recover Shandong.
以督促政府加大收回山东的力度
thank you.
谢谢
Thank you, Mr. Shouchang.
谢谢守常先生
everyone.
各位
Government of the Republic of China .
中华民国政府
Has agreed to the petition of Qingdao citizens.
已经同意了青岛市民的请愿书
He wan min zhe.
和万民折
Now the submission ceremony officially begins.
现在递交仪式正式开始
ladies and gentlemen.
女士们 先生们
Just now, I passed President Xu Shichang of the Republic of China.
刚才我经中华民国徐世昌总统
And Qian Nengxun's entrustment.
和钱能训总理的委托
Officially accepted on behalf of the government.
代表政府正式接受
People's petition and people's discount in Qingdao .
青岛民众的请愿书和万民折
At the same time, I am also influenced by the United States and Britain.
同时我也受美国 英国
Entrusted by the French Embassy in China.
法国 意大利驻华使馆的委托
Accept and forward on behalf of.
代为接受并转交
Letters of Appeal from Qingdao Petition Group to the above four countries .
青岛请愿团致上述四国的呼请信
President Xu Shichang asked me to tell you.
徐世昌总统让我转告大家
The mood of the government of the Republic of China and Qingdao people .
民国政府和青岛民众的心情
It's the same as the wish.
和愿望是一致的
Attending the Paris Peace Conference.
参加巴黎和会的
Government delegation of the Republic of China.
中华民国政府代表团
Has successfully arrived in Paris.
已经顺利地到达了巴黎
They will join the victorious countries.
他们将和各战胜国一起
Discuss and resolve.
商讨并解决
Relations and interests between China and Germany after the war.
战后中国和德国的关系和利益